<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
  <rss version=".092">
    <channel>
      <title>LitKicks.com: October Earth</title>
      <link>http://www.litkicks.com/</link>
      <description>a worldwide conversation: oct 1 2004 to oct 31 2004</description>
      <language>en</language>
           <item>           
             <title>Living in Time</title>
             <description><![CDATA[William Faulkner's 1929 novel <i>The Sound and the Fury</i> tells the tragic tale of the Compson family through the eyes of four characters: Benjy Compson, Quentin Compson, Jason Compson, and the family servant, Dilsey.  The novel's second section, told from Quentin's perspective, intersperses the last day of his life with the memories of his father and his sister Caddy that haunt him and lead him to suicide.  <BR><BR>The following passage opens the section:<BR><BR>"When the shadow of the sash appeared on the curtains it was between seven and eight oclock and then I was in time again, hearing the watch.  It was Grandfather's and when Father gave it to me he said I give you the mausoleum of all hope and desire; it's rather excruciating-ly apt that you will use it to gain the reducto absurdum of all human experience which can fit your individual needs no better than it fitted his or his father's.  I give it to you not that you may remember time, but that you might forget it now and then for a moment and not spend all your breath trying to conquer it.  Because no battle is ever won he said.  They are not even fought.  The field only reveals to man his own folly and despair, and victory is an illusion of philosophers and fools."]]></description>
             <link>http://www.litkicks.com/BeatPages/msg.jsp?tag=Time</link>
           </item>
           
         
           <item>           
             <title>Hearts of Darkness</title>
             <description><![CDATA[The discoveries of Christopher Columbus are being celebrated today in the USA, and we'd like to spend the day contemplating the world's legacy of discovery and conquest.  Joseph Conrad's <I>Heart of Darkness</I> takes us not to America but to the African Congo, where Belgian entrepreneurs have set up a profitable but horrifying trading empire.  In the early pages of the novel, the narrator arrives in Africa to discover a scene of disconcerting inequity: <BR><BR>"A slight clinking behind me made me turn my head. Six black men advanced in a file, toiling up the path. They walked erect and slow, balancing small baskets full of earth on their heads, and the clink kept time with their footsteps. Black rags were wound round their loins, and the short ends behind waggled to and fro like tails. I could see every rib, the joints of their limbs were like knots in a rope; each had an iron collar on his neck, and all were connected together with a chain whose bights swung between them, rhythmically clinking. Another report from the cliff made me think suddenly of that ship of war I had seen firing into a continent. It was the same kind of ominous voice; but these men could by no stretch of imagination be called enemies. They were called criminals, and the outraged law, like the bursting shells, had come to them, an insoluble mystery from the sea. All their meagre breasts panted together, the violently dilated nostrils quivered, the eyes stared stonily uphill. They passed me within six inches, without a glance, with that complete, deathlike indifference of unhappy savages. Behind this raw matter one of the reclaimed, the product of the new forces at work, strolled despondently, carrying a rifle by its middle. He had a uniform jacket with one button off, and seeing a white man on the path, hoisted his weapon to his shoulder with alacrity. This was simple prudence, white men being so much alike at a distance that he could not tell who I might be. He was speedily reassured, and with a large, white, rascally grin, and a glance at his charge, seemed to take me into partnership in his exalted trust. After all, I also was a part of the great cause of these high and just proceedings."]]></description>
             <link>http://www.litkicks.com/BeatPages/msg.jsp?tag=Conquest</link>
           </item>
           
         
           <item>           
             <title>What Life Is</title>
             <description><![CDATA[According to Edith Wharton, American novelist and acolyte of Henry James, "Life is either always a tight-rope or a feather bed. Give me the tight-rope."<BR>]]></description>
             <link>http://www.litkicks.com/BeatPages/msg.jsp?tag=Wharton</link>
           </item>
           
         
           <item>           
             <title>The Business of the Poet</title>
             <description><![CDATA["Write what you know" is a familiar axiom to writers, and is obeyed as much as it is ignored. For poets, poetry is often considered the language of emotion, and the work is often an extension of the poet's own emotional landscape, a place for the writer to express, purge, or deal with his or her own feelings.<BR><BR>It is perhaps for this reason that the following statement from T.S. Eliot's essay, "Tradition and the Individual Talent", might seem surprising:<BR><BR>"The business of the poet is not to find new emotions, but to use the ordinary ones and, in working them up into poetry, to express feelings which are not in actual emotions at all. And emotions which he has never experienced will serve his turn as well as those familiar to him. Consequently, we must believe that 'emotion recollected in tranqulity' is an inexact formula . . . Poetry is not a turning loose of emotion, but an escape from emotion; it is not the expression of personality, but an escape from personality. But, of course, only those who have personality and emotions know what it means to want to escape from these things."<BR><BR>]]></description>
             <link>http://www.litkicks.com/BeatPages/msg.jsp?tag=Eliot</link>
           </item>
           
         
           <item>           
             <title>Flip Flop</title>
             <description><![CDATA[At the Republican National Convention in August, John Kerry took a major beating for his inconsistency on various issues.  For instance, in the Vietnam era he was both a combat veteran and an anti-war protestor.  In recent years, he's attacked Bush's war against Iraq but also voted to support it in Congress.<BR><BR>This type of behavior may go over better in literary circles than political ones.  A surprising number of writers have chimed in on the worth of an indecisive mind.  Here are a few samples:<BR><BR>F. Scott Fitzgerald: "The test of a first-rate intelligence is the ability to hold two opposed ideas in the mind at the same time, and still retain the ability to function." <BR><BR>Ralph Waldo Emerson: "A foolish consistency is the hobgoblin of little minds, adored by little statesmen and philosophers and divines. With consistency a great soul has simply nothing to do. He may as well concern himself with his shadow on the wall. Speak what you think now in hard words, and to-morrow speak what to-morrow thinks in hard words again, though it contradict every thing you said to-day."<BR><BR>Walt Whitman: "Do I contradict myself?  Very well, then, I contradict myself (I am large, I contain multitudes.)"<BR><BR>Oscar Wilde: "Consistency is the last refuge of the unimaginative."]]></description>
             <link>http://www.litkicks.com/BeatPages/msg.jsp?tag=FlipFlop</link>
           </item>
           
         
           <item>           
             <title>Anger</title>
             <description><![CDATA[Poet Adrienne Rich often used a deep exploration of her emotions to map her poems.  The following excerpt from the poem "The Phenomenology of Anger" (1972) represents an exploration of anger that leads Rich to address the role of emotion as a catalyst in our lives.  <BR><BR>7.  I suddenly see the world<BR>as no longer viable:<BR>you are out there burning the crops<BR>with some new sublimate<BR>This morning you left the bed<BR>we still share<BR>and went out to spread impotence<BR>upon the world<BR> <BR>I hate you.<BR>I hate the mask you wear, your eyes<BR>assuming a depth<BR>they do not possess, drawing me<BR>into the grotto of your skull<BR>the landscape of bone<BR>I hate your words<BR>they make me think of fake <BR>revolutionary bills<BR>crisp imitation parchment<BR>they sell at battlefields.<BR> <BR>Last night, in this room, weeping<BR>I asked you: <i>what are you feeling?<BR>do you feel anything?</i><BR> <BR>Now in the torsion of your body<BR>as you defoliate the fields we lived from<BR>I have your answer.<BR><BR>...<BR><BR>10.  how we are burning up our lives<BR>testimony:  <blockquote>the subway<BR>              hurtling to Brooklyn<BR>              her head on her knees<BR>              asleep or drugged</blockquote><BR> <i>la via del tren subterraneo<BR>es peligrosa</i><blockquote>many sleep<BR>               the whole way<BR>               others sit<BR>               staring holes of fire into the air<BR>               others plan rebellion:<BR>               night after night<BR>               awake in prison, my mind<BR>               licked at the mattress like a flame<BR>               till the cellblock went up roaring</blockquote>Thoreau setting fire to the woods<BR> <BR>Every act of becoming conscious<BR>(it says here in this book)<BR>is an unnatural act]]></description>
             <link>http://www.litkicks.com/BeatPages/msg.jsp?tag=Rich</link>
           </item>
           
         
           <item>           
             <title>Black and White</title>
             <description><![CDATA[Bob Dylan wrote "My Back Pages" in 1964.  It was one of his first famous songs to break out of the "protest singer" mold and present a more existential, visionary world view.  Even for protest singers, the world in 1964 no longer seemed black and white.<BR><BR><I>Crimson flames tied through my ears<BR>Rollin' high and mighty traps<BR>Pounced with fire on flaming roads<BR>Using ideas as my maps<BR>"We'll meet on edges, soon," said I<BR>Proud 'neath heated brow.<BR>Ah, but I was so much older then, <BR>I'm younger than that now.<BR><BR>Half-wracked prejudice leaped forth<BR>"Rip down all hate," I screamed<BR>Lies that life is black and white<BR>Spoke from my skull. I dreamed<BR>Romantic facts of musketeers<BR>Foundationed deep, somehow.<BR>Ah, but I was so much older then,<BR>I'm younger than that now.<BR><BR>...<BR><BR>In a soldier's stance, I aimed my hand<BR>At the mongrel dogs who teach<BR>Fearing not that I'd become my enemy<BR>In the instant that I preach<BR>My pathway led by confusion boats<BR>Mutiny from stern to bow.<BR>Ah, but I was so much older then,<BR>I'm younger than that now.<BR><BR>Yes, my guard stood hard when abstract threats<BR>Too noble to neglect<BR>Deceived me into thinking<BR>I had something to protect<BR>Good and bad, I defined these terms<BR>Quite clear, no doubt, somehow.<BR>Ah, but I was so much older then,<BR>I'm younger than that now.</I><BR>]]></description>
             <link>http://www.litkicks.com/BeatPages/msg.jsp?tag=Dylan</link>
           </item>
           
         
           <item>           
             <title>Problem of the Century</title>
             <description><![CDATA[William Edward Burghardt DuBois, a controversial American author, editor and civil rights leader, was a sharp critic of Booker T. Washington's apologetic stance on racial equality.  In his groundbreaking 1903 work, <i>The Souls of Black Folk</i>, DuBois wrote:<BR><BR><i>Herein lie buried many things which if read with patience may show the strange meaning of being black here in the dawning of the Twentieth Century.  This meaning is not without interest to you, Gentle Reader; for the problem of the Twentieth Century is the problem of the color-line.</i><BR><BR>W. E. B. DuBois' statement about the color line proved prophetic in a century that saw leaders, thinkers and writers such as Marcus Garvey, Langston Hughes, James Weldon Johnson, Richard Wright, Malcolm X, Martin Luther King Jr., Stokely Carmichael (Kwame Ture), Huey P. Newton and others confronting the issue of race from multiple angles.<BR><BR>Now, just over a hundred years since <i>The Souls of Black Folk</i> was published, we'd like you to consider the problem of racism from your perspective in this century.  Has this issue touched you personally?  How?<BR>]]></description>
             <link>http://www.litkicks.com/BeatPages/msg.jsp?tag=Race</link>
           </item>
           
         
           <item>           
             <title>Going Back To Uruk</title>
             <description><![CDATA[Many of the earliest extant writings on this planet are odes to the honor of war.  <I>Gilgamesh</I> originated around 2000 B.C. in Uruk, a Mesopotamian city-state near the Euphrates in modern-day Iraq.  It's the story of a heroic king, and like other later ancient writings from the Bible to Homer it is infused with dramatic military situations and numerous invocations to the moral glories of war:<BR><BR><I>O Shamash, hear me, hear me, Shamash, let my voice be heard.  Here in the city man dies oppressed at heart, man perishes with despair in his heart.  I have looked over the wall and I see the bodies floating on the river, and that will be my lot also.  Indeed I know it is so, for whoever is tallest among men cannot reach the heavens, and the greatest canot encompass the earth.  Therefore I would enter that country, because I have not established my name stamped on brick as my destiny decreed.  I will set up my name where the names of famous men are written.</I><BR><BR><BR>]]></description>
             <link>http://www.litkicks.com/BeatPages/msg.jsp?tag=Gilgamesh</link>
           </item>
           
         
           <item>           
             <title>Life After Death?</title>
             <description><![CDATA[The concept of an afterlife has always had literary overtones, from Dante to Charles Dickens to Alice Sebold.  To write about afterlife is to confront the reality of death, and many writers have struggled for enlightenment on this subject.<BR><BR>French author and philosopher Albert Camus broached this subject when he wrote, "There is but one freedom, to put oneself right with death. After that everything is possible. I cannot force you to believe in God. Believing in God amounts to coming to terms with death. When you have accepted death, the problem of God will be solved -- and not the reverse." <BR><BR>Other writers prefer a more sardonic approach.  In <i>Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy</i> Douglas Adams offers, "Arthur hoped and prayed that there wasn't an afterlife. Then he realized there was a contradiction there and merely hoped that there wasn't an afterlife." <BR><BR>Today, we ask you to consider your feelings and philosophies on spirituality and religion as they relate to the concept of an afterlife.  <BR><BR><BR>]]></description>
             <link>http://www.litkicks.com/BeatPages/msg.jsp?tag=God</link>
           </item>
           
         
           <item>           
             <title>Trout Fishing in October</title>
             <description><![CDATA[<i>I left the place and walked down to the different street corner.  How beautiful the field looked and the creek that came pouring down in a waterfall off the hill.<BR><BR>But as I got closer to the creek I could see that something was wrong.  The creek did not act right.  There was a strangeness to it.  There was a thing about its motion that was wrong.  Finally I got close enough to see what the trouble was.<BR><BR>The waterfall was just a flight of white wooden stairs leading up to a house in the trees.<BR><BR>I stood there for a long time, looking up and looking down, following the stairs with my eyes, having trouble believing.<BR><BR>Then I knocked on my creek and heard the sound of wood.<BR><BR>I ended up by being my own trout and eating the slice of bread myself.<BR><BR>The Reply of Trout Fishing in America:<BR><BR>There was nothing I could do.  I couldn't change a flight of stairs into a creek.  The boy walked back to where he came from.  The same thing once happened to me.  I remember mistaking an old woman for a trout stream in Vermont, and I had to beg her pardon.<BR><BR>"Excuse me," I said.  "I thought you were a trout stream."<BR><BR>"I'm not," she said...</i><BR><BR>The above passage, from Richard Brautigan's 1967 novel, <i>Trout Fishing in America</i>, is a classic example of the author's humorously surreal take on the world.  While there are numerous ways to interpret this, perhaps one of the most interesting is to look at it as a passage on the often startling difference between perception and reality.<BR><BR>As writers and readers, we often confront (and regularly blur) the line between these two entities.  For the second day of October Earth, we'd like to ask you to consider what happens when what you perceive is not the same as what is.<BR>]]></description>
             <link>http://www.litkicks.com/BeatPages/msg.jsp?tag=Trout</link>
           </item>
           
         
           <item>           
             <title>The Details of Victory</title>
             <description><![CDATA["Once you hear the details of victory, it is hard to distinguish it from a defeat."<BR><BR>Jean-Paul Sartre, the French philosopher, was passionately involved with progressive causes through his life.  He lived through the horrors of two world wars, and many of his writings depict the plight of the idealistic intellectual trying to find the right path in a hostile and violent world.<BR><BR>Right now, the world is debating the meaning of America's war against Iraq, and there are no easy answers to be found.  A careful look at the current situation in Iraq is to apprehend a swirling mass of opposing extremes: freedom, oppression, compassion, cruelty, generosity, greed, helplessness, aggression.  Trying to make sense of it all is about as easy as reading Sartre's "Being and Nothingness".  <BR><BR>For the opening day of October Earth, we'd like to tackle the question of war head-on.  Please make a decision about which side of the this debate you stand on, and tell us why.  Please read the question on the right and share your answer with us.<BR>]]></description>
             <link>http://www.litkicks.com/BeatPages/msg.jsp?tag=Sartre</link>
           </item>
           

  </channel>
</rss>
